[Music]
what seems to be going on pretty
reliably so far is finding relationships
of complementarity at an mutual
correction rather than adversarial
processing variety attempt to dominate
or destroy on that that I think for me
not only what we're talking about but
the exemplification of how we're talking
and how we're entering into a
relationship how are we we are reap
writer or we're reprioritizing we're
moving off of the product and the
position and trying to really move into
process and participation and that's
well that's that's always been very
important to me because as you know I
aspire towards the Socratic ideal but
that is now even more so the case for me
because I see that ability to enact
functional as opposed to dysfunctional
and adaptive as opposed to maladaptive
collective intelligence and bring it
into something like collective
rationality so that it can effectively
so that we can effectively aspire to
collective rationality and wisdom um
that has become has become very very
central to me and like so that the
process of all this discussion over the
last year meeting all of you guys and
women and then engaging in the work on
the after Socrates project cuz all has
just it has intensified and very
dramatically deep and it was already
deep I believe but is it intensified and
dramatically deepened my commitment to
the Socratic ideal of deal logos that
has now become um sort of very very I
would say that sacred to me and the way
I talk about in this series right okay
if you've already breached on some
aren't breached you've already touched
on some of the things that we were going
to discuss sure the first being
rationality and so you said you said
collective rationality yeah oh so that's
seem to be an interesting idea
and dial logos so so what's the
difference between just ordinary
rationality and and let's say collective
rationality and dialogue and dialogue
goes right so let's let's well let's do
it first what's the difference between
sort of ordinary or comp the common
right good notion of rationality and
there and the notion I'm arguing for and
then we'll do that sort of individually
because that will give me an analogic
basis for them talking about the
collective it is that okay great yeah so
typically and I know this because I
teach I teach on rationality and so I
get to see people's and these are right
educated young people they're right and
so they're sort of the best
representative representative of what we
call folk psychology so within the COG
SCI academic world folk psychology is
the psychological the implicit largely
implicit psychological theories that
most people are carrying around so
people have theories implicit theories
about intelligence about rationality
right right right and it's folk
psychology they haven't listened
theories about how memory works they
have implicit theories about what
concepts are the now one thing we should
put on the table right away
is and this is what I got a lot of time
doing in introduction to cog sign is
most of those folks psychological
intuitions have turned out to be wrong
but they have turned out to be very
wrong and for a kind of important reason
right so so let's say you know our ideas
about rationality or ideas about wisdom
yeah or your ideas about intelligence
you know all of them are very distorted
or a very yep yeah very very skewed are
these about memory let me give you an
example for commemorat because it's it's
far enough away from our topic that'll
be a little less controversial a little
a little easier to just sort of
establish so many people we have all
these metaphors in fact that to speak
this we think of memory as like like
like a room in which we store things and
we go in there and we retrieve it and we
search through our memory and so the
metaphor we have is kind of like we like
a library and we're sending people in
and they're moving around and why
and this kit brings me to the point I
wanted to make we have these folks
psychological notions because we have to
remember that in our folk psychological
context we are not primarily interested
in explaining phenomena we're interested
in primarily predicting and training so
right there's a language of explaining
in a language of the training okay
here's what I want to say if I want to
train your memory it's a really good
thing to use that idea of a room right
here's a this is you see it on Sherlock
right you have your you have your memory
palace or your mind Palace right you
have this room it's called the method of
low side and it let's say I'm gonna talk
to Andrew and I first talk about
rationality so you know III get a room I
like a space maybe this house that I'm
in I'm Phil you're familiar with it the
library is where I'm gonna talk to
Andrew but rationality so form an image
of you in the library and there's books
and there's knowledge and alright right
and then and then I'm not going to talk
to you know Andrew perhaps about
transformation well that's the kitchen
on a picture Andrew in the kitchen and
he's he's doing and so what I do is I
make all these images and they're in
different places and what I do is I
actually search I go from room to room
to room in my mind this is a powerful
way to train memory the the ancient
orders could use this technique to
memorize speeches that will last like
six hours so it's really powerful way to
train your memory and it goes very well
with all those metaphors the thing is
our memory doesn't work like that at all
that's good language for training it but
you you don't actually have that sort of
you know search cereal search because
for example can you please tell me
Justin Bieber's phone number mmm no no
you don't know you don't know it no you
didn't scroll through all of your phone
numbers and realize that it wasn't there
you just know is that like a heuristic
or something or well no there's it's
it's it's that it's there's a heuristic
there's also a kind of parallel search
there's a kind of memory probably in
neural networks as opposed to located
memory like in standard computers and
you know and your memories aren't stable
you're constantly reconstructing them
you're constantly rewriting them that's
why confident I listen it alright
confident eyewitness testimony
forty-nine percent of it is inaccurate
forty
9% of it is wrong huh right because
confidence measures how meaningful you
find the experience not how accurate
that it is or you know we think you know
in a library things that are you know
that are relevant to each other are
stored close to each other but like in
your memory if I give you a vice a color
red say another color as quickly as you
can so red red okay or say another color
red blue okay now give me a a word that
rhymes with blue true okay so red is
close to blue and blue as close to true
is red close to true no no memory so
although we talk about memory I'm in
training with that and it seems so
intuitive to us that that must be how
memory works and that's not how memory
actually works you see that I'm trying
to show you just in these sort of Pony
eat you know dog and pony examples that
your memory doesn't actually work that
way in fact it's taken us a long and and
attention doesn't work just like the
spotlight and all kinds of yeah so I'm
jumping ahead to say that this is what
you mean about wisdom to write is seeing
for yourself deception right or are
these these forms can leave their lead
to self-deception or they can lead to a
greater understanding that depending how
we use them or how transparent they are
to us right so though what I'm trying to
get at
yes I that's I think a very appropriate
way of reframing what I'm saying if we
don't pay attention to the difference
between our folk psychological language
of training and our scientific language
of explaining we can equivocate we can
confuse them together and thereby deeply
deceive ourselves now I and get into all
kinds of New Age nonsense
well a mule Age nonsense but also we
could fail to more powerfully even use
our memory when we're studying for a
test so so people think well the best
way to study for a test to sort of read
the material over and over again and
rehearse it because it's like sort of
you know writing over and over again on
the same spot in the library to make it
but that's not the best way to try and
study for a test for example because
you're not actually using your memory
for how it actually functions oh can I
can I just do a slight aside here yeah
because this is fascinating to me I was
talking to Zach Stein recently Geno's
act you know yeah if I could I have
talked yes yeah he's a brilliant guy
anyway told me that his that he's a high
achieving dyslexic yes and he described
his mind and it seemed to be very
similar to mine and I'm pretty sure that
I have the same thing that he has oh you
read the paragraph first and then you
read the sentence and then you read the
word you don't read from the word up to
the paragraph like you know you're too
in the Gestalt and then it's and then
you have to get to the to the to the
feature right yeah so an ordinary mind
kind of for most I shouldn't say
ordinary because nobody has an ordinary
mind but most people kind of build up
from from maybe the feature to the
gestalt and then a person who has it
sort of has that kind of dyslexia it
doesn't mean they can't read or anything
they just kind of do things in a
different you know different way you
it's a little it's a it's a little bit
more complicated everybody I'm sure
everybody actually simultaneously again
because you're not doing things
step-by-step the way we think in
language yeah here's you know so that's
why we had to get neural networks to
solve what's called the chicken and egg
problem because when I'm reading I to
read the letters in order to read the
word but I need to know what the word is
in order to disambiguate the letters
so you're spontaneously going from
feature to Gestalt and Gestalt to
feature sure right so it's in parallel
again which is not something that's easy
to put into words right it's kind it
doesn't go well with sort of again a
folk psychological understanding of how
we do things
but it's modeled well than neural
networks for example now the thing is of
course everybody's sort of doing that
but there is variation on wit like how
it's skewed some people more skewed
equally some people are more skewed
Gestalt II yeah so my main point of all
of this and thank you because you've
helped me sort of explicate my point
right in this discussion we've just had
is we have to be willing to challenge
our folk psychological notions
rationality yeah because there's right
it's very plausible that like all of our
other folks psychological constructs
well it has some important truths to it
it also has a lot of misrepresentation
and misdirection with respect to the
phenomenon mm-hmm and so why that's a
little bit more challenging for us I
think is is that you know if you if you
have sort of a memory that's not that
great it's a little bit affects your
sort of status and your self-esteem a
little bit but you know I'm not that
much but these terms intelligence
rationality and wisdom they carry with
them a tremendous aspects of our
cognition very very powerful so that's
why people get very very sort of about
notions of intelligence rationality and
wisdom so again we need to pull apart
write our identification with these
processes which of course we should
address it eventually but we need to
pull that apart from our attempt to get
our best understanding of them because
again our eye dentist like all of our a
lot of our my side biases and our
egocentric bias our identification with
these processes can actually deeply
impede us getting a good understanding
of them I needed to say all of that
precisely uncurls I want to challenge
choose standard notions of what it is to
be rational okay go for it okay so one
notion of what rationality is you know
it's kind of the Spock version for the
FRA for those of you you and I have that
generation we know right this idea that
that rationality is logic ality and you
see this in you know there's a lot of
sort of online forums that sort of
that's the model of rationality that
rationality is to be as logical as
possible and mr. Spock sort of
exemplified that and the problem with
that is it we have to we have to set it
into an overarching idea that ultimately
we're goal-directed
we're seeking goals we're seeking to
achieve goals and so one thing we have
to note is that what rationality means
method as a method for us is we're
looking for the most reliable and
systematic way of achieving our goals
right so you say wow but that's flying
logic is the most reliable and
systematic way of achieving truth the
problem with that is it's not true
not because logic isn't relative
relevant to rationality but you can't
identify about snotty with logic and
here's the problem
logic works in terms of certainty and a
completely formal system mm-hmm and what
that means and I'm trying not to try not
to presuppose too much be presumptuous
of what people have seen other series
but what that means is you basically
into a kind of processing that has to
check all of the problem space it has to
check all of the information it has to
check all the possible options you have
to be comprehensive and exhaustive you
have to be kind of like a machine of
some kind rather they'll be human yeah
but nobody can do that like even or even
our best chess playing machines can
search all the possible options it's
common tutorial explosive they can't
search all of these like that the
problem of search is is it still the
profound problem is that it's there's
just too much too much information too
much so if you and everybody knowledge
is this who was working within
rationality Herbert and Simon you know I
think was was it Simon's book I think it
was a Newell and Simon or Simon's book I
think bounded rationality their
rationality is always bounded in terms
of what's actually possible for us
Chania talked about we're in the
finitary predicament and this goes to
the core of my work we can't reason we
can't make inferences on the basis of
all possible options all possible
probability or all possible information
that's common entirely explosive so what
we do is we bound it we zero in on
what's salient you knew I was gonna do
this then relevant then what's right and
and so that means before you can even
use logic you have to have pre logical
processes of problem formulation the
direction of attention
Sergent memory and those are not
obstacles to being right
because they prevent you from being
fully logical they actually facilitate
they constitute you being a viable
cognitive agent if you don't have that
you're gonna be sick the neck the next
text I try to perform I'm gonna hit home
and a tutorial explosion and then I've
committed cognitive suicide mm-hmm so I
for dreaming or something like that
you know a dream is is we don't normally
think of a dream as being rational it
could be but it could it could have a
rational function or I could have yes
what do you mean well more than that I
mean I I think that what you see is but
one plausible account of what dreaming
does is it's a kind of optimization
process on how your brain is operating
mm-hm and so it's not so much the
content of the dream but it's sort of
the way in which your brain is sort of
practicing getting better adjusting what
it finds salient and relevant so it does
weird variations on patterns that you've
sort of acquired through the day and it
sees which one of those sort of optimize
its ability to track and predict and
solve problems that's where you're often
solving your problems in your dreams
right right here right and so and that
that looks all sort of create it's all
illogical but it could turn out to be
rational because it could be actually
optimizing this process of relevance
realization that is so central
especially and here's what I want to
come back if it systematically and
reliably improves your ability to zero
in on relevant information and then I'm
going to add something to that that is
directly implied by that it
systematically reliable in
systematically and reliably improves
your ability to overcome self-deception
then I think that's how we should
understand rationality well rational
practice is a practice that
systematically and reliably improves
your ability to overcome self-deception
and to optimize your ability to zero in
on the relevant information such that
you are more and more capable of being a
good general problem solver and
achieving your goals and that's what
rationality means so it's not logic
ality but it's also not just being
intelligent right because um with
intelligences intelligence is basically
uh Leo and I argue this leo Ferrara and
I argue that
and I think you can make a good case
that a lot of people are implicitly
arguing for this that what we're
measuring when we're measuring
intelligence is we're measuring sort of
your working memory capacity to zero in
on relevant information and hmm the
problem with that is and this is the
issue right very often what I what I
initially might find relevant or salient
is actually a kind of bullshitting it's
actually taking me away right from being
able to solve the particular problem by
paying attention to the wrong things
because my machinery is designating
certain things as relevant or salient
that actually will not help me to zero
in on or track the patterns that I need
in order to find my goals right this is
where you need insight because when you
have an AHA experience you realize oh no
I formulated the problem the wrong way
and I've got to change what I find
relevant and salient and that means if
we have an account of rationality in
which insight does not play a central
role we do not have a good account of
insight because the machinery of insight
is the machinery by which you optimize
your ability to zero in an information
and it's the same machinery you use to
overcome self-deception mm-hmm so the
problem with that with the with the the
idea of it just being intelligent is
rationality so intelligence is what
you're using well there's a lot of if I
could just there's a lot of very stupid
intelligent people right they have the
machineries all there but they're not
using it correctly or that's right
they're not using it in an optimized way
or in a and let's say essica way or in a
or or an on self-delusional way right
okay right and said that's exactly my
point Andrew they're they're they're
your you use your intelligence to solve
your problems but that can generate all
kinds of skewed salience landscapes
capacities for acting immorally
for acting in a self deceptive manner
rationality is what you use in order to
deal with all of that right all of those
if you've side effects generated by
using your intelligence in an adaptive
manner so rationality is is is if
practice rather than something you're
just born with and oh yes no no you're
not that's very important to think to
know that right that one and it's you
said it was aspirational right it's yes
yes become a rational person even though
it seems like an ideal like it's not a
very likely scenario that you would
become 100 percent rational yeah I don't
I I don't even know if that's possible
yeah I don't I don't yeah I don't even
know that's the correct way to frame it
because it it brings with it a sense of
an idea of completeness or finality and
because your relevance really because
your intelligence is a self-organizing
evolving dynamical system and because
the world is a self-organizing dynamical
system there's no there's no sort of
final state you can get into we can say
where you can pronounce now I am forever
free from all process sort of it's all
process well this is this is how I
interpret the first noble truth of
Buddhism I'm not a Buddhism look like
even though you know Alexander says I am
but right all right because but I
interpret it as you know not that all of
life is suffering is that makes no sense
but that no matter where you turn there
is no place in which you can be free
from the threat of self deceptive
self-destructive behavior no matter how
smart you are no matter how intelligent
you are yeah you missed something
wouldn't you you'd always have a blind
spot somewhere oh I have a lot of blind
spots so you know you take a look a lot
of psychology's going through the
replication crisis results aren't
getting replicated well you know what is
robustly getting replicated time and
time again all this stuff about
cognitive bias all this stuff about
self-deception all this stuff about how
intelligence is necessary but not
sufficient for rationality all of that
is very very robust it is not going
through the road application crisis it's
an aspect of our cognition that we
should have very strong confidence that
which means given these two points we
should not think of rationality as
identical to either logic ality or
either to our intelligence up sort of
our
innately given problem-solving capacity
because that's what I think
intelligence is and and and and I think
this would actually ameliorate a lot of
useless debates people don't like the
idea you know that IQ is fixed because
then they think they're doomed right
they think oh no right because you know
and then there's all these objections
and right and but and this is I think
this is an argument I get from stand a
bitch we shouldn't be caring so much
about intelligence and yeah G is a good
predictor it's one of our best measures
of general intelligence you know what I
should all I really care about about you
a rational you are yeah because that's
gonna predict how moral you behave how
how how you can overcome ego centrism
how you're less self-deceptive like an
your mud truck like what about the whole
effective world right because I was you
know I was thinking about how how when I
was talking to you last night
he kind of lives in that kind of a realm
he's he's very rational as well but but
he doesn't he doesn't he doesn't swim in
rational arguments he he kind of swims
in something else or or well but again I
guess I'm I'm I'm still I still have
this narrow definition of rationality
when I know but that's but that's great
what you just that's a beautiful segue
for me because the the so I've two ways
in which are the folk psychological
notion is to narrow it either identify
and it often does it both in a
contradictory manner but it often
identifies rationality with being
intelligent yeah right and right and
therefore fix like intelligence but no
it's not rationality is not intelligence
and rationality is developmental you can
get better and better at matter you
conspire and it's not equivalent to rat
to logic ality just being good at logic
is not it's evidence is clear it does
not make you very rational actually
rationality is about knowing where when
it's about rate rationing it's about
knowing where when and to what degree to
be logical you know this brings what you
just said brings me up to the third way
and the folk psychological notion are is
not cross culturally but ours in the
West is deficient is we limit
rationality to just inferential
processes about belief
they say oh we limited a job to use some
of Mines from a knowledge do we limit
rationality jus just propositional
knowing and that with a goal the sole
goal of rationality is to get true
beliefs which of course is ridiculous
I could get in you know an indefinitely
a large number of true beliefs in my
room by you know you know noting
correlations between how many paper
clips are in the room and how many cups
are in the room like the amount of
information in this room the amount of
true information is overwhelming what we
actually want is true information that's
relevant to us relevant to our
problem-solving tasks relevant to our
moral undertakings etc yeah I was
listening to somebody who was talking
about intelligence I put that in the
article I write it and he said that
wisdom is when you can say so what like
your you could discard all that
information which is important and you
could vote you can narrow in on what
really matters well yes in a deep
existential way not not on on on proton
you know as you say products or or yeah
I mean sometimes our goals are genuinely
epistemic we want to know the true
causes of things yeah but and this is
the point I want to make but if we bring
in the many other ways in which we try
to couple ourselves to reality our
procedural knowledge well that our
procedural knowing well then we want
systematically in reliable ways of
getting and improving our skills a
perspective on knowing well then we want
systematically in reliable way of
improving our right our salience
landscaping and our ability to generate
the sense of right presence our
participatory knowing we want systematic
and reliable ways of getting into the
best right kind of existential mode for
example shall they be in the having mode
right now should I be in the being mode
should I be treating you categorically
should I be treating you in a bit like
all of those kinds of things and how am
i appropriately set you see in the thing
about guy his guy is swimming right
first of all relevance is not cold
calculation it's not logic relevance is
about an act of commitment I am
committing my precious time and
resources in a gamble a risky gamble
that this I care I'm caring about this
rather than that information because I'm
ultimately trying to take care of myself
and take care of it well this word care
seems very important because you know
one of the reasons some people would
would you know want to be trans rational
or have you know post rational
experiences or have experiences that
we're not what they would consider to be
rational with is because rationality
often seems like a cold form of but
you're saying exactly the opposite right
I'm saying exactly opposite so they use
and this goes back to Socrates so the
Socratic platonic tradition right all of
this you know there's argumentative
stuff the inferential stuff is bound up
with also abilities to change
perspective to cultivate software so
that you know a kind of salience lens
that's what we that's one of the
cardinal virtues we usually translate it
very poorly as moderation but it's much
more like your salience landscaping has
evolved so it spontaneously
self-organizes to tempt you towards what
is more true towards more right it's
basically your perspectival knowing has
been trained so that you're much less
subject to right so you you
know usually were yeah this is something
you said in the series usually we're
tempted to what I like you
saying what if we were tempted to do the
good the good or whatever that might be
and wouldn't and wouldn't that be part
of what a wise person has they they
would come into a situation right and
before they're getting into perhaps any
specific inferential processing they're
sort of drawn to what's not only what's
relevant but what's you know well you
know in a problem-solving sense but
maybe what's also relevant in a moral
sense what needs to be addressed you see
that's the thing about Socrates right
and the Platonic tradition right all of
that argumentative stuff is bound up
with love it's profoundly so we see
these you know post romantic tradition
we see these as a potent well you know
spirituality is about love and science
is about reason and the two are opposed
and they're separate but no in the whole
Neil clip Socratic Neoplatonic tradition
they're bound up together in fact
Socrates you know
Socrates claimed
just note erotica he he knew what to
care about he did he did there are some
things he actually did claim to know he
that's a good definition of wisdom isn't
it to know what - yes
- no he he was seeking a rationality of
appropriate caring right now that caring
can be caring for the truth it can be
also caring for by caring about what's
right it can be caring about right
what's beautiful you see all and a lot
of the Socratic dialogue is not about
coming to an argumentative conclusion
trying to bring in the perspectival and
participatory knowing right and and
that's why Socrates often doesn't use
analogies to argument you have to use
his analogies to skills because
procedural knowledge is a little bit
closer than propositional knowledge
dimmers electoral and participatory
right and so he's trying you're bringing
into perspective on than the
participatory knowing because you're
trying to shape it again you often the
dialogues don't end in any kind of
inferential conclusion they're often we
also often leave you well we don't that
were we don't have any clear conclusion
about well may it's like if I guess it's
like it's like good art or something it
doesn't yes it doesn't wrap up the whole
story so you're you you're satisfied
with your product in like a like a
Hollywood movie it it kind of opens a
new Vista for you it opens a new Vista
and it all so it also launches you on to
aspirational transformation so what
you'll see at the end of a lot of these
dialogues is there's no argumentative
conclusion but you'll see that so right
they'll be I there's a dialogue on
courage and there's two people arguing
and it's interesting because they're
arguing about courage and they represent
these two positions I'm but
there's a general and he thinks just his
common sense notion of what courage is
that's that's the correct so we are
every day yeah right he's full
psychological and then there's a guy
who's a sophist and he has this sort of
technical sort of logical definition
right that he's heard from somebody else
right and Socrates rejects both of those
and and and then you get to the end and
there's no conclusion as to what courage
is other than the fact that these two
approaches have been shown to be
inadequate but what you see is both of
the generals say they want their sons to
come and
from Socrates to spend time with
Socrates because that the process maybe
because maybe perhaps courage is is not
something that you can define it's
something that it's it's not something
you you could define in any absolute
sense no and maybe think about Heidegger
inand and what he taught when he talked
about thinking and how concepts a true
concept is something that doesn't have
any kind of finitude to it it just
reveals itself more and more over time
more and more truth over time and and
and and you can't ever pin pin it down
or that's what I'd let goes back to what
I was saying earlier about you have to
get away from models that seek
completeness and I mean the initiative
thing and I think that's exactly the
right so Socrates the point of the
dialogue is you have to step back and
this is why Plato writes dialogues as
opposed to just straight arguments the
point is the you you can't get a
definition of courage but as you watch
Socrates move between these two
positions the skill ax and Charybdis of
going along you get a sense of how to
get on the track how to aspire to
courage and that Socrates is reliably
honest so you develop a kind of trust in
following Socrates because he has
exemplified even though he can't
explicate courage mm-hmm so the idea
that I would like to bring into a lot of
current practices like guys circling is
to not always just be participating in
the process but also to step back and
look on what we're exemplifying in the
process so like you know encircling
you're doing all these things to
maintain the flow of the distributed
cognition mm-hmm and everybody who's
feeling that it's very meaningful but
whatever you step back and say yep but
what is meaning what is meaning in this
situation what and not just abstractly
because you've got the phenomenology as
active its engaged and you have multiple
people there that have multiple
perspectives on it and you can start
doing something like a Socratic dialogue
well what is it to be meaningfully
connected and then and then what you can
do is check with you know are we still
exemplifying the phenomena we're trying
to explicate it's not even just a new
you try to keep the two by
tightly coupled together so you don't
you're constantly moving Chris Master
Pietro and I talked about this in the
chapter we wrote on dr. logos you
constantly sort of you've got your
constant moving but in an integrated
fashion between fear theory and theory
abut ween you know theorizing and then
going back and really theory really
loosing it out and yeah yeah yeah really
extremely experienced in it in action
mmm-hmm and so rationality again is
would be for collective intelligence
would be to try and find systematic and
reliable ways of getting that kind of
pattern of communication and connection
between people in place hmm very very
interesting yeah it seems to me that
that's very important now especially
because we're in a very anti rational
time or source like everything is about
sensation and feeling and I don't want
to be you know say that feeling is bad
but but everything is about everything
is based on you know clicks and likes
and it's experience and salience yeah
right yeah yeah yeah so that seems to be
very important too yeah okay that you
know there's the ocean of experience and
then there's also stepping out and
coming back in and going in and out of
that mmm I think it's very needed and I
would want I wouldn't want to say that
let's use the Socratic model we just had
and also some of the points we've made I
think our our time is irrational or
lacking in rationality in two senses in
one sense like a general the one general
who just lets go with my intuition and
my impulse and whatever just sort of
comes to me and then we have no no let's
be rational let's be tell you exactly
what I was gonna say as well yeah yeah
it's this this hyper rationality which
is is I don't think it's rationality at
all what you would say is not
rationality all right
yeah I I'm still have this deaf I still
have the folk definition of rationality
in my head so it's almost hard for me to
have the conversation until I
redefine the term rationality and like I
said you're struggling against not only
just sort of the familiarity of your
folks psychological conception you're
also struggling against the fact that we
have set up all these cultural patterns
of identification and evaluation around
these terms right and we reward people
and we claim this and we claim that and
that's also I think acting as an
obstacle to trying to get back to a
notion of rationality that actually
starts to overlap with wisdom you see
that's what they these two needs do this
notion of rationality has just been sort
of you know practical you know
intelligence problem-solving or the
notion of rationality is just being sort
of good logic allottee it tells me
nothing about wisdom basically it
doesn't really help me it doesn't help
me with that systematic and reliable way
of cutting through yeah heading
to what's relevant and then also
aspiring write properly aspiring so that
my development is constantly evolving
with reality in it in a sort of
continuous coupling none of that is
given to me by those models so you talk
to you in McGilchrist recently oh my god
so I I you know I'm very interested
because you know your story is almost
the opposite of his but you're probably
saying the same thing you know he talks
about it he talked about brain right
brain you talk about opponent processing
very much working together those seem to
be kind of analogous whereas he says
that rationality is just cutting the
worlds up into bits and turning us into
bureaucratic monsters and and we need to
get more into the right brain world of
you know so a feeling and and and you
know or context and and the right of the
experience the embodied experience of
life you know and so how did you how did
your conversation go how did you you
we're gonna talk again it went so well
we really clicked really deeply so you
know rebel wisdom they recorded it it
will be released at some point
so a couple points on that first of all
because this goes to what we were
talking about earlier perhaps a more
helpful way to think of right and left
is to think and and I actually brought
this up with the in in person and he
said it was completely convergent with
him so I have good reason to believe I
can speak sort of something that we are
agreeing on because I have in-person
evidence right to say so you can because
I came at it I hadn't read Ian's work
until about two weeks before I met was
gonna meet it okay as I came at this
stuff and I came to similar conclusions
from all the work I do on insight right
inside problem-solving so a good way to
think about the right hemisphere is it's
a way it works more in terms of the
gestalt yes exactly yeah and so it likes
wide open attention and it looks for for
like for for it's sort of pursuing
pattern completion right right whereas
the the left hemisphere is more feature
lis oriented and it does things in a
step-by-step matter it's doing it's
doing something more like a pro running
a program than trying to complete a
pattern it's sort of building features
up step by step by step right and so
think about the kind of attention it
needs it needs very narrow focused it
looks for a clarity or it doesn't like
ambiguity now here's the idea of
rationality when he live in the left
brain but not that out in ax t and and
and that's I think part of our Cartesian
heritage that's to identify rationality
with analysis and Mary Cohen has brought
this point up and I think to you
identify rationality with analysis is a
mistake I think it's it well for all the
reasons I've already articulated it
truncates what rationality should mean
especially because rationality is vote
ratio finding the patterns rationing
right getting the getting the proper
context it so it's a much more
logistical notion so why do we have
these two well the left hemisphere is
very good for well-defined problems
problems in which you have a really good
representation of your initial state
your goals state what the
actions and obviously I already know it
tells you and already know about what
you already know
yeah it's familiar to you in a deep way
so a multiplication problem would for
you for many people a very well-defined
familiar problem now compare that to the
problem of avoiding predation yeah what
does that look like well I'm avoiding
you know well you know what's my initial
State
I'm not sure right right you know get a
notepad and start you know what the goal
state looks like right very clearly and
this is the thing and do most of our
real-world problems this is why that
that notion of rationality of analysis
are is so limiting most of our
real-world problems are actually like
the problem of predation they are
ill-defined problems you and I are
trying to have a good conversation right
now
mm-hm what's the initial condition well
we're not talking that's not very
helpful what's the what's the what's
what's the goal state look like well I
don't know the art does every good
conversation look the same no they have
some feature what should I say what
should i do should I rave my hand shall
raise my voice should I like watch it
like right you see what I mean or go on
a successful first date or tell a joke
you can't draw a picture to tell
somebody this is how you go on a
successful first date give them you
can't offer you a to be yeah I can't
give a program help program yeah right
but you can't that doesn't mean it's
useless there are way we get better at
going on dates we get better at
conversation and think about that think
about that what I just said how that
goes back to what Socrates is doing in
the dialogues right you get better at
becoming courageous right but that
doesn't mean I can give you a formula or
a program for orange yeah right now when
I when I was trying to eat with like I
said we really so ian makes a
distinction it's kind of the reverse of
the distinction I make so it I think it
was it was largely semantic he actually
makes the distinction between
rationality and reason Yeah right
exactly that's what I wanted to bring
yeah and I picked up on reason is great
because reason is holistic and again you
you put everything together and we
should be reasonable but but
but we're over emphasizing rationality
and cutting that's you know here's what
I can say then very clearly I'm using
rationality the way Ian uses reason
exactly using reason the way I use
rationality right right so what he
rejects is what I consider to be that
truncated folk psychological notion of
rationality that I think does not
represent anything that will help
facilitate our aspiration towards wisdom
hmm so although there is a problem maybe
the problem I'm seeing is that that that
notion of rationality is so deep it's
like it's Cartesian it's woven it's
woven into the scientific worldview it's
woven into our epistemological models
and those that worldview and those
epistemological models get woven into
our psychological models they're woven
into Freud they're woven into young
they're woven into many yeah that's but
you that's why you that's why you that's
why guy is so attracted to Heidegger
because Heidegger is like he's
profoundly trying to break out of that
whole Cartesian way of thinking about
belief and truth and rationality and
he's trying I think to get us back to a
way of understanding rationality kind
so maybe what he calls thinking is call
rationality totally Tobin Heidegger
calls thinking and what he McGilchrist
calls reason yes yes just sending
different semantics areas here or yes I
agree agree so the the argument that I
have sort of why I think rationality is
actually an appropriate word is reason
tends to be associated with reasoning
but the throm with reason it's equivocal
it can go to reasoning which means
inference and argument we go to
reasonable which means this kind of
thing we're talking about so that's why
I'm a little bit whereas the
etymological origin of rationality is
Rati oh it's finding proportion that's
it's putting things into proper relation
it's getting the proper perspective is
the relationship yeah exactly it's more
about pattern completion then commend
running a program to completion those
are two very very different things also
we need to be
at times what do you mean by that
because I well I
we need them as you say break frame
right so for trying to be reasonable all
the time if you know this is why there's
shaman is there you know there were
shamans and you know - as you talked
about in your series yeah break out of
the yeah nine dart problem or yep
so but this brings me to this brings me
to an important point I would want to
say because I actually I actually have
brought this argument up I presented at
a conference at a couple conferences
this idea that disruptive strategies are
actually important for optimization
in fact there's systematically and
reliably important for optimization so
if you're running a neural network for
example you just let it just sort of run
right it'll over fit to the data it'll
it'll find patterns in its sample and
really pick up on those patterns in its
sample that don't actually general
generalize to the population you know
this is sampling bias right and so
because the machines are so powerful and
your brain is way more powerful than any
neural network so think about how you
can really zero in right and get bound
to you can over fit to your particular
sampling of data so what do you do in
the neural networks well you you
actually disrupt the network you shut
off some you shut off half the nodes or
you throw noise or static into the
system and what that does is it makes
the neural network we self organize
right and that we've stopped
organization actually allows it to now
generalize in ways it couldn't
generalize before yeah so you have to
throw disruption in I recently did some
graph breathing technique he's like that
and I I don't do psychedelics but but
but that kind of experience just it
throws you into these wild sort of
spaces right right and it's wild and
that and then you come out the other
side is if you've gone into Alice in
Wonderland and you come out the other
side sort of like and you have to
reassemble your ordinary existence and
hopefully you've got some insight after
doing that
yeah and what what happens is your
perspectival and participatory knowing
have been shifted and so a new course of
development is actually available to you
yeah
think about think about like when you're
in that when you're in that space it's
like what happens in dreams a lot of
variations are being thrown at like sort
of generated options are being created
that open up what's called the state
space it opens up the possibilities that
that your brain can actually get itself
into like my brain is a machine that's
constantly making itself into the kind
of machine and you want to periodically
like with a neural network you want to
open up the options it can consider not
only the options in the world it can
consider but the options for what kind
of machine it can be it's those two
together at the same time right and so
if it and you can see this even an
insight problem-solving if I give you an
insight negate and I moderately distract
you or even throw some static into the
picture some noise that will actually
help to trigger your insight of course
yeah okay so get better at the game
right if you're tripped up but yeah but
do it the right way they 2000's right so
there's an X there's a kind of expertise
or you have to do it in the right way
right there's no formula but you have to
do in the right way but there are
systemic and reliable ways of getting
better at doing that disruption
now here's my argument this disruption
is really indispensable to optimization
there are systemic and reliable ways of
doing that
wouldn't that therefore be integral to
our account of wisdom that these
disruptive processes and that means that
although they're non inferential they
have actually no propositional content
whatsoever because they're basically oh
yeah zero propositional content right
but nevertheless they move you towards a
more optimal that optimization of you
know I have more options in what kind of
cognitive being I can be yeah and where
are more options about what kind of
world I can dwell within and that is
making you more rational yeah and well
if ya again it's counter intuitive yeah
well I guess the rational world that we
live in
often feels like a kind of prison right
yes we're trapped in caught conceptual
models of things and that's one of the
reasons why you would you know you would
you would want to break frame or you do
fasting or you know or going into nature
and you know have all kinds of let's say
of those kind of experiences well this
brings me to another point and and you
know I think Ian's bang on about the
left and right stuff but there's another
there's another opponent process that
you need to bring into the discussion
here which is the relationship like
because we're constantly toggling
between being tasks centered and mind
wandering right um and the and the point
of mind wandering I would argue at least
one of it's funny wondering is to break
frame it's - its - its to bring in some
mild distraction take you into a weird
so that's key again our guy sorry I keep
saying I because I'm in France but I
think that's that's what guy does well
see Heidegger was about wandering so
what he's planning to do is I think what
heidegger's doing is you know you just
stay on the path that's like the machine
that's gonna over fit right and what you
need to do is you need to wander a bit
right you need to go off almost like in
mind-wandering and what that does is
allow you to you know introduce the
noise introduce some variation break
some frame so that so but you keep
moving forward but you're now actually
improving your connectedness to the
world rather than just getting to your
destination on your path yeah and that
also speaks to the pathology of
montmartre modernity right is that we
don't maybe we don't wander enough we
don't we don't want it enough han says
we don't we fill up the space too much
with with with you know information yeah
and salience and and
we like that's why also pointed out Hans
notion of lingering it's not only that
we fill up this space we right we will
take Heidegger being a time that your
being is at hint inherently temporal
right and so you are wait you are
respectable and participatory knowing of
time because you don't know time in any
other way right the Augustine famously
said this I know what time is until
somebody asks me what it is because
right you only know time by being in
time right by being a temporal thing but
so your existential mode with respect to
time how you're experiencing that's the
wrong word that's the only word I have
how you're participating maybe let me
let me use that word how you're
participating in time existentially has
a huge impact on the kind of being you
can be and so hans point is we are
moving into a culture in which we can't
leader we can't we can't we can't flow
with things wait everything is atomized
we're going down like minutes and
seconds
is his cut up that's exactly the idea
how - yeah mm-hmm and so you don't get
any flow you get you get the you get
sort of the salient second right you
know um so a lot of people have met talk
to me about this and you know we're
seeing we're seeing this consistent
trend towards the death of melody in
popular music that we're losing melodic
complexity and there's this compressed
sound all the time with mp3 it's extreme
compression of sound and screams
compression of sound and salience in
salience and intensity are taking up the
place of right complexity and
development
you don't have to follow a long piece of
music and go through all kinds of
transformation you can instantly without
effort get sort of hit by the same
product right yes exactly
yeah and that's and so what that means
for us is that like I said it's also
that we can't linger we can't stay with
things in a way that affords us
during the projects of aspiration yeah I
think I've liked going to the galleries
like I live near in Paris and there's
all these galleries and how many people
look at a painting you know yes how many
people go into and actually just stay
with the painting and look at the
painting and and find out a valuable
experience right yes most people would
would would what sort of you know look
at the painting and like take a picture
snapshot of it with their iPhone and say
I'd been there and I've seen that
painting what but but that that goes to
just what I said the point is to collect
atoms to collect moments that are
atomized and are removed from a flow of
development they're just snapshots yeah
I think I think their remedy to that one
of the remedies I've seen is probably
meditation in some sense because yep for
for our modern times you know I think
because it's how else can you how else
can you because there's so much stimulus
all the time how else can you take a
break from that and I think I think I
think I think both meditation and
contemplation are needed sure you have
to break frame and make frame I think
being able to enter into the Ilocos to
enter into a conversation oh that's
another thing for me like that's like
I've been meditating for years but but
you and guyun that's a that's a new kind
of possibility for me I hadn't really
thought of that so much well I mean this
is the this is part of the platonic
notion that training your rationality in
the sense I've been arguing for and
training your sociality are deeply
interpenetrating things that's why he
presents his philosophy in a dialogue
because you're not you're those two
those two things our ability to connect
to distributed cognition and participate
in collective intelligence and
collective rationality or dare I say
collective wisdom in its it's in
resonance with our individual project of
aspiring to rationality and wisdom these
two things mutually afford and depend on
each other hmm
yeah yeah and also I was just sort of
thinking about how how why this sort of
conversation is compelling to people and
stuff which it's kind of a weird thing
it's like a homeless or like homeless
here or something saying that to the guy
last night it's like we're putting in
these videos on YouTube it's not part of
the mainstream culture but it seems to
be there seems to be a need for it for
that kind of kind of totally I think the
the online world I mean it has it has
sort of it has some of the greatest
magnifiers of the things that exhauster
bade the meeting crisis you know but you
know you Heidegger talks about where you
know what I think he's holder lining
quotes where the danger is there there
also right the future grows I think it's
a translation I might have missed
translate it but the basic idea is you
know because it's it's a it's
destabilizing the system it's also but
also it could be an affordance of the
system going through self-transcendence
rather than disintegration you can even
say a death and rebirth of some yeah
kind of thing a shamanic kind of idea
and so what what I think what's
happening with the Chris and I talked
about the meta conversation you have all
these conversations and then what
YouTube is doing is setting up this
thing where people are having
conversations but they're doing them
with the awareness right and their
connectivity to other conversations so
there's not only idea logos within a
conversation there's this Neil logos
that stay in place between all of these
conversations and the way they constrain
and impregnate and engender each other
in this kind of complex self-organizing
dynamic which is really really important
because you see the same thing again at
least analogous and the Platonic
dialogues you shouldn't just ever read
one platonic dialogue that's a mistake
you should be because you should read
all of the ecosystem again of yes all of
yes exactly all of the dialogues are
speaking to and influencing and changing
and affecting each other in powerful
ways and we're doing something and now
it gets to that here's a dialogue and
one with guy and then there talk to each
other and speak to each other yeah now
that will inform me to speak to you and
then somebody else might get a little
something out of this and bring it yeah
yeah yeah again to bring a Socratic
platonic thing and there's a possibility
for Aragog eh that's that reciprocal
opening that you and I have talked about
before so the conversation when it when
it moves into dialogo so you've got the
reciprocal opening that's happening and
that of course is again a kind of love
right because when people get into
difficult opening they at the experience
they have the experience of the
affective state love isn't an emotion
it's a higher-order affective state but
it's a it's an effective state right up
love enough to get how the rationality
and the sociality and the love are all
bound together how should I put them all
back together uh-huh got you yeah
they're they're all sort of in little
islands over here and they need to come
again one place exactly that's why
that's why I'm as critical of
Romanticism as I am of empiricism
because both of them keep although those
things apart but for different reasons
for different positions that they hold
and different epistemologies and
metaphysics and I think all of them are
therefore equally at fault for keeping
those things apart no I mean I'm doing a
bit of a you know a gloss my other
question actually I wrote that down it's
like what can we what can we take from
Romanticism because romanticism is so
powerful it's so you know so that's the
thing
so it's so you know we need that and on
some level especially in our you know
online world people are so blase and
stuff we we need to we don't know I have
a feeling that that we need we need
grandeur
sort of experiences and emotions that
that that were being too polite and
timid and it's it's like being in a cage
of some kind of Romanticism is like
trying to break that cage a little bit
it is I mean so again I was going to
engage in some self-criticism and you've
actually allowed me to do so so thank
you for that I mean I I try to make a
distinction between what I call decadent
romanticism which is sort of a folk
psychological version of romanticize
Cheryl right and sometimes I have not
been careful enough about that and so I
do apologize to people because you have
to take a look at like just like I don't
think you should talk about
post-modernism it's like I'm sure you
should zero in on particular thinkers in
particular arguments because there's
variation and so here's what I want to
say and especially the I don't even know
I want to call them romantics that the
early the you know the early post
contents like Schlegel and people like
that I I think they're actually saying
things remarkably similar to what I'm
trying to argue for and but the
romanticism that you get especially
Rousseau's version of Romanticism yeah
which is a prototypical version of it is
it singable romanticism and I want to
say this I want to try and convey
something and I'm going to say it
carefully and hopefully provocatively
it's closer to the truth than the
impaired and that empiricism and
therefore it's it's the it's more
dangerous it's more dangerous because
it's not contained and in that it's in a
collective experience it's it's sort of
okay there's that so you've got Russo's
glorification of individual subjectivity
okay you know that's clearly a true self
right I mean he does have stuff about
the general will but when we're talking
about how he's the father of Romanticism
this the the glorification of individual
subjectivity is there the idea that you
come with a true self that you must be
true to which is antithetical to the
idea of aspiration
so it's antithetical to the ceramic
ideal of aspiration the idea that
this subjectivity should be thought of
like so
what was so stalking about it he he's he
does not express enough worry about the
problem the problem of self-deception
sort of separating all of this from
rationality as I've tried to describe to
describe it right to put the Socratic
notion of overcoming the ways in which
we deceive ourselves and
ourself this exploration and expression
of your individual subjectivity in your
capacity to imagination of will for
imposing an order on the world well
think about how that could just be
filled with self-deception honey you
know you're like projection and bias and
Prejudice like all of those things right
and so romanticism doesn't it's it's
separated itself off from deep concerns
about human the human proclivity for
self-deceptive self-destructive behavior
which is why we we get the almost the
romantic trope of you know how living
romantically ultimately is kind of
self-destructive of the people who try
to help to live that way you can see
that in you know sort of weathering
Heights kind of stuff right oh yeah my
mother read that book like 20 times
let's say so there's that it's so
appealing to people yeah I guess there's
a self-destructive element in that or
well they also a hatred of civilization
or a hatred of your efforts to to you
know you know build things and yep yep
so there there is a lot of so it was a
terrific and I want even catch both
senses of that word it was a terrific
terrific strategy for breaking the frame
of empiricist enlightenment for breaking
the frame that John Locke gave us of the
tabula rasa mind and the world imposes
itself in the finger of the world right
so my mind it was a great counteracted
that yeah but I think it generates its
own frame that needs to be broken and
broken Bo that's well said you know
that's great
hmm hmm that's why Heidegger is so
interested in being because right annan
challenging the idea that we should
impose our will on the world right that
the world is just a standing reserve
because the part of what heidegger's
trying to get us to remember is you know
Locke has the mind as a blank slate but
Rousseau has the world as a blank canvas
upon which we paint our subjectivity and
Heidegger is trying to get us to
remember no no it's not a blank canvas
it's a world it is deep and profound and
beyond us yeah yeah yeah that's great
hmm and it discloses itself you know as
it will who's feyza huh I've heard two
pronunciations and I keep getting
corrected by both camps on how I should
pronounce the Greek term I I was I was
brought in my intellect in my undergrad
everybody pronounced it as fuzes but
I've been told no it's not more like
Jesus or Isis or something or physics
right that's the word disclosure and in
hiding where did we get physics from but
it means it means the way in which
nature blossoms from itself blooms from
itself but also the way in which nature
loves to hide itself oh yeah yeah yeah
right right mm-hmm
yeah yeah yeah Heidegger is another
subject yeah that's yeah and I mean I'm
having excellent conversations with
Johannes about this and I think it's up
on his channel I'm gonna put up the
dialogue that I had with you excellent
we're gonna have it up and he and I and
I are gonna talk shortly about sort of
Heidegger but I'm gonna put up the
dialogue I had with Johannes I'm doing
it I'm doing a couple new series right
I'm doing the minding media series but
I'm also doing this series I'm entitled
it yet but what I'm having just I'm
trying to exemplify dialectic which is
the psycho technology of engendering
deal logos I'm trying to exemplify that
and get into these like these
discussions where we're exemplified
and explicate a what did what does
spirituality mean within the scientific
worldview and the meeting crisis what
does that mean for us
uh-huh right we had an accent
conversation on Heidegger and science
and technology yeah I loved it I saw
someone half of it and I was released
later the other do you think you've said
what you wanted to say about about about
wisdom and and and rationality and what
is there any is really loose ends here
yeah I want to say one more thing about
sort of clarifying a bit the
relationship between wisdom and
rationality I think that we should think
of ecologies of practices for each one
of the kinds of knowing that make us
more rational so you know ecologies of
practices for propositional knowing and
cognitive practices for procedural
knowing ecologies of practices for
prospective and participatory so you
have some examples well I think the
ecology of practice for propositional
knowing we've we've got I mean that's
what we and we think we know what we're
talking about when we use this term I'm
going to use but if you do any
philosophy around this we don't actually
know what we need and this is the term
science science is about whole ecology
of practices and it's bound up with
history right I mean yeah and it's this
way of trying to get to be as rational
as we can because I the scientific
method it's actually a family of methods
is not about coming to certain
conclusions it's about really trying to
reduce the influence of self-deception
on our inferential processes and our
propositional knowing that's what
actually is going on the site science is
largely about trying to set things up so
that we can break through our patterns
of self-deception right now you have
similar things right in your procedural
knowing and this is where you know I
think the martial art traditions give us
fantastic example well how to cultivate
ecologies and practices and this is what
Rafe Kelley is just doing some amazing
and important work right on this kind of
thing nah
right the way he's using parkour and
integrating it with martial art practice
and mindfulness but go and see some of
the his videos see some of the dialogues
I've had with him mm-hm the perspective
of knowing well that of course that's
where all the stuff on attention and
awareness the mindfulness practices
right the flow induction practices are
really important knowing that's where
the deal logos that's what this is yes
okay yeah participatory knowing we're
trying to we're trying to we're trying
to alter our not just our thoughts but
our identities the way in which we're
mutually shaping each other the way
we're being the way us and the world are
engaging so I will I'm entering into a
reciprocal opening with you but together
we're also trying to enter into a
reciprocal opening with the world right
and so yeah mm-hmm great great so here's
my point there let's say there are
reliable systematic and reliable kinds
of rationality for each of the kinds of
knowing there's propositional
rationality procedural rationality
perspective of rationality and
participatory then you need something
that optimizes the relationship between
all of those rationalities hmm that's
wisdom
hmm so wisdom is about the relationship
it's about all between between all it's
about it's kind of the the whole yep
okay okay I see it's kind of its wisdom
is very much a kind of meta rationality
right yeah least that's how it
I think that I think that it's not
identical to what that like gnosis that
the world gnosis came to me to me is
that each one of them I tend to think of
APIs to me for a propositional tech made
from for procedural noesis for
perspectival
and gnosis for participatory and then I
think Sophia and phronesis describe the
two aspects of wisdom the bottom-up
aspect that's from Mises and the
top-down house so when I when I'm
coordinating those four kinds of knowing
I need a powerful I need a lot of
bottom-up and I need a lot of top-down
I need phronesis and I need Sofia uh-huh
awesome
wow that's that's a whole structure you
well you know it goes towards the work
I'm doing with Daniel Craig on the
cognitive continuum by the way I just
want to mention I have an IndieGoGo
campaign for and I'm not getting any
money from that campaign or from the
book the money is I'm a university
professor I get a salary I'm fine
Daniel the student and he's committing
to working on this book with me and it's
not even on writing he's generating art
he's putting - he's basically key like
the movie producer as well as a
co-author and so this money is to help
to support him as he's doing all of this
work but that what we're talking about
in the cognitive continuum is exactly
this because I think and I try to argue
that in the series I think we can get
also instead of like instead of building
a mystique around these terms and this
is where like Evan Thompson's work I
think is really important also Steven
Bachelor both of them are now post
Buddhists because they object to
Buddhist Buddhist exceptionalism the
idea that Buddhism is somehow a special
or privileged religion compared to all
the rest because it's somehow was
scientific and I object to that as well
I I knew would and he would and you have
to remember that both Steven and I know
I've met Steven had dinner with him and
Evan is a colleague and friend of mine
they're both deep your deep friends of
Buddhism these are not hostile yeah yeah
go outside right and so right they
to the fact that the what's happened is
this let's take a term like
enlightenment it's bound up with entire
cultural projects and worldviews and it
often has this mystique around it
remember let me tell you how this
frustrates me you know I've asked
Buddhist you know how many people in the
world do you think are enlightened right
now and they'll say well probably no one
and then it's sort of my mom minded go
but what the heck is it for that right I
mean the term is meaningless right and
so so I think instead just like I try to
give you'll allow me I tried to
reverse-engineer wisdom I tried to build
it up out of fear right and and in terms
of what we wanted to do and Howard well
I think we should do the same thing with
enlightenment
I think enlightenment is we should
reverse engineer it oh it's a terrible
word isn't it it's just it's a terrible
word and what I think we should do is
right this is how I want to use the word
and maybe we should use a different word
because because of the critiques that
Stephen and especially Evan are making
but I want Amy so once I have wisdom the
two are gonna be bound together
I want a wise ecology of practices that
it helps me transform cognition
consciousness character and communitas
so that I can systematically and
reliably overcome the perennial problems
of self-deception and self-destruction
and afford enhancing all of the
connections what I call religio that are
so constitutive of meaning in life for
me that's enlightenment because it has
to be some other deep metaphysical thing
I don't care because I want to be able
to help people alleviate you know the
suffering of the perennial problems and
afford the flourishing of enhanced
connectivity to themselves to each other
in the world hmm
yeah so you want to stay within in the
real I guess I want it and I'm going to
stipulate how I'm gonna use the term and
I'm trying and so there I'm saying I'm
not using it ambiguously I'm trying to
not use it in a way that is loaded into
a particular I mean I can't be
completely free of a cultural worldview
but I'm not trying to bind it to a
particular culture
tradition instead I'm trying to pick up
on what science gives us access to is
universal features and principles of our
cognition and then you know the notion
that is pragmatically engineered for a
specific set of what badly and widely
needed goals hmm you know so I guess the
reason this this term is so offensive is
that it kind of I was just thinking that
it kind of it implies a an end product
or something it's so a deeply critical
of that a deeply critical of sort of the
perfection completion aspects of the
term enlightenment are deeply critical
of the people refused to acknowledge
that they're sliding between something
that's explaining the world and
something that's evaluating the world
right it's to use sort of technical
language and this is one of evans
criticisms like you don't want to you
don't want to confuse your best
description of how reality is with your
your best sort of normative claims about
how things should be
those aren't those aren't the same and
so for example why does that matter well
science isn't doing that second thing
science is not in the project uh this is
the way things should be this is you
know this is moral this is moral
excellence this is a static excellent
science isn't it it doesn't have the
machinery for doing that science is
about trying to give the best
explanations
it doesn't really afford us you know
aspirational projects and so I think
Buddhism is an aspirational project and
therefore to pretend that it's sort of
like it's it's a it's also deeply
scientific ah that's a category mistake
yeah it's a category mistake for sure
it's not yeah so it's just one way of
knowing right and then Buddhism might be
another way well and I think addresses
something that science doesn't address
which is aspirational project of
transformation and self transcendence
and right and that it's gonna have a
historical cultural aspect to it right
yeah so I think what we should do with
what we're trying to do what Daniel are
trying to do is well let's look at
different cultural models and then let's
look at that this engineering this
pragmatically engineering sense
enlightenment that I've just given you
and let's put them into dialogue and try
and get some convergent thing that maybe
has less of the off-putting mystique of
a lot of because you know when you when
you talk to people about enlightenment
it's it verges on the you know the
supernatural and the person is becoming
godlike and it's like well if that's
what it is
then and I don't mean it's
disrespectfully to Buddhist but I'm not
interested in that I'm really not
interested in in and godlike people or
yeah I mean I'm interested I you know
I'm interested in the aspiration to
becoming more and more at one with sort
of the sacred depths of reality but
that's very different from it's a that's
a question of growth not a question of
some ultimate state or yes some ultimate
state and some and some ultimate
transhuman State mm-hmm so there's a bit
of a Nietzsche and critiquing in my head
here about stop a young you should be
overcoming yourself but you should never
be abandoning your humanity in that
project so VC he I guess I guess I'm
gonna say something a little provocative
here I I find humanity ultimately good
enough this is why I love Conrad so much
the heart of darkness you compare Marlow
and Kurds Kurds takes on the hubristic
past of becoming a god right and then he
suffers the horror of the horror of the
world Marlow makes conscious decision to
act to exercise restraint and stay with
his humanity right that he will not even
though they'll follow the journey he'll
go all the way to seeing hurts he will
never abandon his humanity that's where
the heart of darkness I think it's such
a powerful be important well that seems
to be the Bodhisattva vow if if I'm
defending Buddhism a little bit okay
sure
uh-huh is is is is to do just that isn't
it it's not it's not to sate yeah I
think the Bodhisattva it might have been
a bit of a corrective than in Mahayana
for Tara Baden the because the body rots
over is therefore right much more
different than the are heart in some
ways yeah
that's a good thought I hadn't thought
about that but yeah that because there's
a there's a commitment to you staying
with humanity yeah you know and and that
every being is your they call it mother
being it's like every being as your
mother and and you you have to liberate
every being it's a wild sort of idea but
it's it's a sort of wild heroic idea
that's but it but it's not very rational
certainly not I think it's rational in
the way always is Russia here we go
again
it's just I can't get the folk
rationally ID out of my head but I like
that I'm sorry
implicit is a way of deeply binding the
Enlightenment project to humanity yeah
it's a good point that's a good point
under that's a really good point I
hadn't thought of that